<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony and warning of the Presbyterie of Edinburgh against a late petition tending (in the scope and design thereof) to the overturning of the ordinances and truth of Christ in this Church, Octob. 5. Anno. Dom. 1659.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. Presbytery of Edinburgh.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14703</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13339438</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13339438</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99133</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64450)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99133)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 336:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony and warning of the Presbyterie of Edinburgh against a late petition tending (in the scope and design thereof) to the overturning of the ordinances and truth of Christ in this Church, Octob. 5. Anno. Dom. 1659.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. Presbytery of Edinburgh.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99133:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY AND WARNING Of the Presbyterie of <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Againſt a late PETITION, Tending (In the Scope and Deſign thereof) to the Overturning of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Truth of CHRIST in this Church. <hi>Octob.</hi> 5. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1659.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:99133:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99133:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A TESTIMONY and VVARNING of the Presbyterie of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Againſt a late PETITION, tending (in the ſcope and deſign thereof) to the Overturning of the Ordinances and Truth of CHRIST in this Church.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>October</hi> 5. 1659.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T cannot but ſadly afflict all tender-hearted Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and lovers of the intereſts of Chriſt, that the Lord having for diverſe years ſet the beauty of His Ornament in majeſty among us, and afterward having ſet up His fire in <hi>Zion</hi> and His furnace in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to take proof of our proficiency under His Ordinances, there ſhould ſo much droſſe and ſcum appear among us; that our outward chaſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhould be attended with ſo many ſpiritual judgments, and that the licentiouſneſſe of the times hath not only looſed the reins to Atheiſm, irreligion and profanity in many, and opened the door to Seducers from without, to break-in upon this Church; but that even from among our ſelves ſome have ariſen, ſpeaking perverſe things, who have ſpit in their Mothers face in the day of rebuke, and made defection from the Doctrine of Chriſt and His precious Ordinances, which ſhe in mercy enjoyeth. As theſe things (in the holy and righteous diſpenſation of God) have bred us no ſmall exerciſe and grief of heart in our ſtations; So it cannot but augment our ſorrow, when we find that diſtemper not only conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing to be a ſnare and trial to the Lord's people under our charge, but that it is upon the growing hand: And that now ſome men are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to make apoſtaſie themſelves, and to do what they can, by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and activity in ſeduction, to enſnare others; But they will alſo bend their utmoſt endeavours to pull down the hedge about the Lord's Vineyard, and to overturn all ſettlement of Religion among us, that ſo a liberty may be proclaimed, and encouragement held forth, to all who pleaſe to run wilde (under a pretence of <hi>new light</hi>) in all abominations
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99133:3"/>of errours and deluſions, until (if mercy prevent it not) the Lord's Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation here be turned into an howling wilderneſſe, and ſo the way be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for Antichriſt (who is not aſleep in theſe times, and whoſe hand is, not without cauſe, ſuſpected by the ſober godly in theſe actings) to make a prey of us, Or the minds of people be ſo plagued with Atheiſm, by reaſon of their own and others reeling in the matters of God, that they will prove as capable of an impreſſion of Heatheniſme as of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</p>
            <p>Of theſe pernicious practices, we have of late met with a ſad inſtance, (which calls us forth to give our Teſtimony at this time) in that ſome, upon deſigns beſt known to themſelves, have projected, and (as we have the charity to believe) enſnared others to joyn with them in a <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> for making void and aboliſhing all Civil Sanctions eſtabliſhing the Doctrine, Diſcipline and Government of this Church, (the fruits of the many prayers and ſad ſufferings of the Godly in this and former ages) that ſo they may enjoy a vaſt Toleration and encouragement in imbracing vileſt errours, which they are pleaſed to ſet off under the ſpecious names of <hi>juſt Liberties</hi> and <hi>Gospel-priviledges.</hi> This unnatural practice, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from among our ſelves, and from ſome of theſe who once pretended to ſpeak of a great bleſſedneſſe in building up what now they would deſtroy, and in enjoying what now they abominate; though we believe it will not ſignifie much, upon the account of thoſe who proſecute it, with diſcerning men who know them, and whom they grieve in this matter; And in that reſpect we could very eaſily have paſſed it as a matter of litle moment: Yet we could not but tremble to finde ſuch a Spirit among us. And as we are called of God to ſtand in the gap, in our ſtation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any hazard to Truth and Religion appears in this Church: So we held our ſelves more nearly concerned in this buſineſſe, ſeing it is aſſerted to be the Petition of ſome within our bounds and charge. And though we have hitherto contented our ſelves with bearing teſtimony againſt their way in our ordinary Miniſtrie, if peradventure God might be pleaſed to reclame them from the errour of their way; Yet being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the unceſſant activity of ſome of them to have their deſign effectuated, we could not ſatisfie our ſelves, as having ſufficiently exoner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our ſelves to their conſciences, or done our duty to theſe of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective charges, without the ſuperadding of this joint Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>If we ſhould inſiſt to deſcant upon the Title and Subſcribers of that Petition, we might ſay many things, which neither would be pleaſant to them to hear, not have we any delight to rake into. While they deſigne themſelves <hi>well affected perſons,</hi> if they mean in reference to piety and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, it would be but little pleaſing if we ſhould give the true cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of ſundry of them who are known to us, and within our bounds, what ſome of them have been in all the turnings of theſe late times, and what they yet are; This will (we truſt) make our pains needleſſe as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99133:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>to this purpoſe, that as it is known, how the body of the truly godly, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and people, throughout the land, do abominate and mourn over their way, however they have differed in other things among themſelves; So we are confident, wherever they are known, their piety (whatever it be) will not be perſuaſive to commend this courſe in the eſteem of any diſcerning godly men. We wiſh they had given a greater proof of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe and piety, than to aſſert in that very Title, that they are perſons <hi>in and about Edinburgh.</hi> For, unleſſe they make moſt of the corners of this Land to be in and about it, this will be found a manifeſt untruth; There being but a few of the Names we have ſeen at that Petition within all our bounds, and the moſt of them gathered in the Countrey, many miles from this place. That which we think moſt ſtrange in this conveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, is, That diverſe perſons, profeſſedly oppoſite to the way of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> whoſe principles and way have been already laid open to the world, in their true colours; yet do joine with them in ſigning that Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to which the hands of moſt of that Sect are gathered through the Countrey. This as it gives us cauſe to believe the truth of what is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly informed, of their gathering hands to ſeverall Copies of that Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſeverall parts of the Countrey (ſome of the Petitioners little knowing with whom they joined in it) which at laſt they put together in one paper: So it gives us to underſtand what a liberty the deſigners of that Petition intend, even no other than what will comprehend theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> who joine with them, ſome of whom have publiſhed in print under their hands, not only vile reproaches againſt the Miniſtrie of this Church, but groſſe errours againſt the truth of God, as namely (to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in ſome particulars) That the godly in this life are without ſin; That the light whereby every man that cometh into the world is enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened, is not the light of nature, but a perfect light ſufficient to ſave them who will follow it; yea, Chriſt himſelf; That it is not a naturall man's duty to pray; That men are able to fulfill the law of God; and that it is a Doctrine of Devils to ſay, God commandeth men that which they are not able to performe; That the Scriptures are not the word of God, but the declaration of the word, and the words.</p>
            <p>Theſe and diverſe other groſſe errours about Election and Reprobati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Univerſal Redemption, &amp;c. publiſhed by ſome of the Petitioners, do abundantly clear what a deluge of abominations they plead to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured in. And albeit they have endeavoured to conveigh their deſign more cloſely in their <hi>Petition;</hi> Yet their Agents have ſpoken their mind more fully in their <hi>Proviſo:</hi> wherein they crave, that none diſſenting from the Nationall Profeſſion of the Doctrine and Church-diſcipline here eſtabliſhed, be debarred or moleſted, but enjoy equall protection and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragment in the exerciſe of their Church-profeſſion, provided they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and do not make uſe of this liberty to colour any licentions practices, and it be not extended to Popery or Prelacy: and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99133:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>all this notwithſtanding any lawes made to the contrary. This is indeed a Toleration as large as any that ever hath been pleaded-for by the wildeſt of Hereticks, and very far from that modeſty that hath appeared in any judicious and ſober men, though otherwiſe enclining to modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſome differences. Hereby they would cut the ſinnews of all co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive power or cenſure in matters of Religion, either by the Magiſtrate, or by the Church, and are not content to be ſecured againſt any Civil reſtraint to be laid on, unleſſe alſo all Civil Sanctions eſtabliſhing the Reformed Religion and exerciſe of Church diſcipline be abrogated, or made void. They do not content themſelves to plead for Toleration in matters of Church-conſtitution and Government, but in matters of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine alſo, and that in ſuch a latitude, that if they profeſſe faith in Chriſt, they muſt go free; And, what Hereticks, how vile ſoever, will not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe ſo much, if they turn not Heathens, Turks, or Jews? All theſe other cautions, wherewith former conceſſions of liberty to diſſenters, are guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as, that they muſt profeſſe faith in the holy Trinity, acknowledge the holy Scriptures to be the revealed Word of God, that they publiſh not horrid Blaſphemies, that they revile not the Miniſtry or their Aſſemblies, nor diſturb them in the worſhip of God, &amp;c.) all theſe are here paſſed over in a general of profeſſing faith in Chriſt, and being free of licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious practices. And we might very juſtly enquire of them, upon their principles, why they would ſeclude Popery and Prelacie, more than the reſt, and that not only conſidering how the very body of Popiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine may conſiſt with profeſſing faith in Chriſt, aſwell as other dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable errours; And learned men before us have demonſtrated what a progreſſe Popiſh opinions have already made under the colour of new lights (if not alſo by Popiſh Emiſſaries their inſinuating themſelvs among ſeveral Sects for that effect) But we would gladly know what arguments they can bring from the Word of God for ſecluding thoſe as corrupt Opinions and Religions, which will not militate aſwell againſt other er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, even owned by ſome of them. This alſo may further diſcover the deſign of theſe Petitioners, and the iniquity of their deſires, that they are not contented to plead for forbearance, or protection only, in their way, but that they, though never ſo erroneous, enjoy equal encouragement with the Sound and Orthodox. A thing condemned even by thoſe who yet in many caſes plead for a Toleration, and moſt unjuſt in it ſelf, that thoſe who profeſſe the Truth, ſhould not only extend pity to ſpare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded men, but encourage and maintain them in their pernitious wayes.</p>
            <p>We cannot but be confident, that, through the bleſſing of God, the very diſcovery of the iniquity of this courſe, will break the ſnare to all thoſe who are not given up to wantonneſſe of mind, for not receiving the Truth in love, and are not driving deſigns to root the true Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion out of this Land. And indeed, if men turn not Scepticks and void
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99133:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>of all Religion, but do acknowledge there is truth and errour in the world, and that men ought to be eſtabliſhed in the preſent Truth, and not to reel every day, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. (for, how elſe could men either preach any thing as a truth, or how could they die with comfort, or ſuffer for any truth, as not knowing but a new day might produce new light?) then it muſt certainly be an iniquity to let men run looſe to do what is right in their own eyes, and to give no leſſe encouragement to the groſſeſt of Hereticks than to the faithfull friends of Truth. If Hereſie be a work of the fleſh no leſſe than Adultery, Murder, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. If erroneous Doctrines be damnable in themſelves, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. and no leſſe prejudicial to the ſouls of others than a Gangrene in any member is to the body, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17, 18. And if Seducers by theſe doctrines be no leſſe dreadfull to the Church than grievous wolves are to flocks, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.29. It muſt be great cruelty, not only to ſuffer, but to encourage ſuch to run on to their own perdition, and to ſeek the perdition of others, provided they hold faſt a generall profeſſion of faith in Jeſus Chriſt. If unity in Doctrine and Worſhip be a mean of eſtabliſhing and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Church; (as the practice of the Apoſtles makes clear, who finding the Diſciples troubled, and their ſouls ſubverted with diſputes and errours brought-in among them, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.24. do eſtabliſh them and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to their encreaſe; by their Decree ſuppreſſing the errour, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.4, 5.) And if, upon this account, a Miniſtery be appointed to bring the people of God to unity in the truth, and keep them in it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5, 8, 11. with 12, 13, 14. It muſt he an unqueſtionable cruelty to ſeek encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſet up that which cannot but retard the progreſſe of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and fruſtrate the labours of the Miniſtery. In the dayes, wherein God hath promiſed that he will give his people not only <hi>one heart,</hi> but <hi>one way,</hi> Jer. 32.39. And that not only <hi>the Lord,</hi> but His <hi>Name</hi> alſo, (or Ordinances and way of profeſſion) ſhall be one, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.9. and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt hath prayed, that His people may be one, as a ſpecial mean to prove the truth of Chriſtian Religion, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.20, 21, 22, 23. They muſt be very ſinfully imployed, who in ſtead of mourning over, or ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to repair the too many breaches that already are, or being ſenſible of the ſad prejudices redounding thereby to the work of the Goſpel, do beſtir themſelves ſo actively to multiply them, and to be encouraged in ſo doing. And if ſuch a Toleration hath produced ſad fruits, even in Churches where Religion is not ſetled, How much more abominable is it, to ſeek it in this Church, which, in the great mercy of God, is ſetled in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government, to the preſervation whereof, both Nations are engaged by the Oath of God? This cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly is nothing elſe but to endeavour to pluck up the hedge planted by God about His Vineyard, and to open a door to the atheiſticall and profane under pretence of new lights, publickly to avow their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all Ordinances and Truths of the Goſpel, to the grief and ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening of all the truly godly.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99133:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>It is neither neceſſary nor poſſible, in this brief Teſtimony, to deſcend particularly into this Controverſie, or to condeſcend upon the many qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications neceſſary for the right ſtating thereof, or to propound and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the arguments confirming the truth. Theſe are extant in the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Writings of others before us, to be peruſed by all who deſire ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and theſe Petitioners have ſaved us a labour, in propounding their deſires in ſo large terms that they ſeclude nothing that beats the name of Chriſtianity, except only the names of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Prelacy:</hi> Nor will it ſuffice them that any ſhould plead for a permiſſion or forbearance to them, unleſſe they be encouraged and countenanced alſo. Therefore we ſhall only give a brief hint of our principles and grounds in this Truth of God, for the eſtabliſhing of the ſouls of his people.</p>
            <p>We are not ignorant what an <hi>odium</hi> is caſt upon us and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt eſtabliſhed in this Church, as if it were full of rigidity, and tyrannically executed by us againſt all who diſſent from us. But as we have been very ſparing to cenſure any who have made defection from the Doctrine and Government of this Church; So the world, and the conſciences of theſe who at any time have been cenſured, will bear witneſſe for us, that theſe Cenſures have been drawn forth with all meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and long-ſuffering, after the uſe of all previous means enjoyned us by Chriſt. And as to our principles, we profeſſe we are very far from that rigour which ſome would charge upon us, as if we held that every leſſer difference ſhould bring men preſently under the laſh either of Civil or Eccleſiaſtick Cenſure, and that no difference of opinion can be ſuffered by us. We are clear that in many things of common practice in a Church, there may be an agreement by Accommodation, though diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of judgment remain about the things themſelves. We acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge alſo that mens opinions do not fall under this Queſtion, ſo long as they do not ſpread and divulge them to infect others, nor endeavour to propagate them by ſchiſmatical and ſcandalous wayes: We are alſo convinced, that all matters of difference are not of alike weight and importance, ſo that men muſt either renounce their opinions, or elſe incur Cenſure, or be denied protection: We do readily yeeld that (as we all propheſie but in part, ſo) men in a Church may compoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, by putting an end to contentions, though they be not all of one judgment; and herein we judge the Apoſtle hath ſet the rule before us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. We yeeld alſo, that as ſevereſt Cenſures and Puniſhments are not to be inflicted for every offence; So a great difference is to be put betwixt active Seducers, and them who in ſimplicity are miſled. But (judging it needleſſe, in dealing with theſe Petitioners, to dip any further in this buſineſſe) this we hold to be agreeable to the Word of God, That Chriſtian Magiſtrates and Church-judicatories, ought to be ſo far from conniving at, or encouraging, that they ought in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective places, and with that prudence and meekneſſe that becometh, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99133:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>to reſtrain ſuch groſſe and damnable errours, as are alreadye vented by ſome of theſe Petitioners, and may be comprehended under the generall termes of their deſire, and the promoters thereof; and tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whether they erre in the matters of faith, or in what relateth to the ſtan, ding of a viſible Church, which is the pillar upon which truth hangeth and which being overturned, expoſeth the truth to hazard.</p>
            <p>That this duty is incumbent to every Church in reference to her own members, is moſt clearly aſſerted in Scripture, where ſtopping the mouths of Hereticks, their rejection and excommunication are recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by precept and example, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.10, 11. and, 3.10. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19, 20. We find Churches cenſured by Chriſt himſelf for the neglect of Diſcipline againſt falſe Teachers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14, 20. and others com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for their zeal in this particular, though found faulty in other things, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2, 4. And ſeing there are no Churches within theſe Nations, though of a different Conſtitution and Government from ours, who do not claim and exerciſe a power of Diſcipline over their own members; we ſee not how the like liberty can be denyed to this Church over her own members, when they make defection from her. As for Civil Powers, we are ſorrie to find, that however the Scriptures pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe them, as Nurſing Fathers to the Church; Yet many now would turn them mere Spectators of the wrongs done to Chriſt and His truth, ſo long as their civil peace is not diſturbed, as if they ſhould be <hi>Gallio's</hi> to care for none of thoſe things, and as if equall protection and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragment, of errour as well as truth, were the only duty of Chriſtian Magiſtrates, which Hiſtories record to have been the great engine of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate for overthrowing the Chriſtian Religion. A prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple this is contrary to the very light of nature in the moſt refined Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, none of which would admit Innovations in Religion, though ſome did otherwiſe upon politicke conſiderations, making Religion a ſlave to their intereſts. And though they erred in the application; Yet in that and the like generall principles the Lord leads them as witneſſes againſt His people in their way of ſerving the true God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.10, 11. That the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was expreſly contrary to this Toleration, is, we ſuppoſe, denied by none, and yet the moſt of theſe plea's now urged for it, taken from the fallibility of men, liberty of conſcience, &amp;c. were of as great force then as now. Nor will they perſwade conſcientious men that theſe do not oblige us now, till they make it out that moral tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, (ſuch as theſe are) puniſhable then by God's command, muſt have a law of immunity and encouragement now, and that what is enjoyned in the fourth Command, is not moral and perpetual, that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Maſters in their families, and Magiſtrates within their gates, ſhould ſee to the Sanctification of the Sabbath, and conſequently to the Worſhip of God publickly performed on that day. And this we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive doth ſo much the more ſtrongly conclude, that we find Law and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99133:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Practice for this, before the judicial Lawes were publiſhed; Not only Abraham <hi>commanding</hi> his children and houſhold to keep the way of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. and <hi>Jacob</hi> ſuppreſſing falſe worſhip in his family, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.2, 3, 4. But even in <hi>Job's</hi> time and Countrey, it was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Maxime, that Idolatry (as well as Adultery) was puniſhable by the Magiſtrate, <hi>Job</hi> 31.9, 10, 11. It is not to any purpoſe to except, that theſe Laws of <hi>Moſes</hi> did chiefly ſtrike (if not only) againſt groſſe Idolatry and blaſphemies: For neither do we urge that every errour ſhould be puniſhed, nor do we know what height of Blaſphemies men may come unto (as we ſee by too ſad experience) who yet may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe all that is requited by theſe Petitioners, in men to be encouraged. And withall, we finde godly Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> have extended theſe Laws further than to ſuch groſſe abominations: for, godly <hi>Joſiah</hi> did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cut off the Prieſts who ſacrificed to Idols on the high places, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.20. but degraded theſe who ſacrificed there even to the Lord only, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.8, 9. as theſe differences of high places may be further clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, from 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.3, 5. with chap. 15.17. and chap. 33.17. As for the dayes of the Goſpel, albeit Magiſtrates were not Chriſtians when the New Teſtament was written, yet we finde ſufficient ground to clear us yet further, that theſe Laws given of old by God are ſtill in force. For, it is fore-propheſied, that the Kings of the earth ſhall deſtroy Antichriſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.16. And why ought they not alſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe other errours, which are but limbs of Antichriſtian Doctrine, and the promoters thereof little Antichriſts? 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 2.18. And we finde, that in times when Chriſtian Magiſtrates were wanting, it did pleaſe the Lord to interpoſe, in a more immediate way, for puniſhing obſtinate offenders, whether in the matter of faith or manners. We finde alſo that the Magiſtrate's power under the New Teſtament, is given him for the puniſhment of <hi>evil doers, Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4. Now, Seduction being an <hi>evil deed,</hi> 2 <hi>Job.</hi> 10, 11. and the Text ſpeaking indefinitly of all ſuch, we would take heed of obtruding our diſtinctions upon it; And that ſo much the rather as Chriſtians are to pray for this benefit by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, that they may live under them not only in all <hi>boneſty,</hi> but in all <hi>godlineſſe</hi> alſo, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2. which can never be without ſoundneſſe in Doctrine, and purity in Worſhip. And whereas ſome except, that unbelief and covetouſneſſe are alſo evil deeds, and yet not puniſhed by the Magiſtrate; We grant, that unbelief and covetouſneſſe in the heart, do not fall under the cognition of the Magiſtrate (as neither is he to cognoſce on ſimple opinions in the mind) Yet, unbelief profeſſed and propagated, and covetouſneſſe put in practice to the prejudice of others, ought to be puniſhed by him.</p>
            <p>We know this truth of God is traduced, as a perſecuting of men for their conſcience, and an encroachment upon the liberty purchaſed them by Chriſt. But as we diſclaim troubling of men for the ſimple light of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99133:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>their Conſciences, if it break not forth in doctrine and Practices; So the Scripture hath taught us, that perſecution is only a putting men to <hi>ſuffer for righteouſneſſe,</hi> and not the reſtraining of abominable errours. And as we know mens conſciences are not their ſupream rule, nor lawleſſe things; So liberty to erre and ſeduce, to vent lies and father them upon the God of truth, &amp;c. is no part of that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty purchaſed to us by the death of Chriſt; But it is in effect a capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and ſnare to be entangled therewith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25, 26. and chap. 3.6, 7. and to be ſervants to corruption under pretence of liberty, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. Yea, to father this upon Chriſtian liberty, favoureth rankly of that old way of turning the grace of our God into laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. We are not inſenſible, how this truth of God hath been abuſed and put to the rack by Antichriſt and his followers, to cruſh the profeſſours of truth: But we have learned, that no truth, though abuſed, muſt be caſt away; nor yet becauſe truth is ſuppreſſed by the enemies of the Goſpel, muſt therefore errours be ſpared by the friends of Chriſt? We acknowledge alſo it is a mercy, if in ſad times truth get, were it but a Toleration; Yet we cannot therefore allow, that errour ſhould have ſo much. Nor do we look upon it as any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing argument, to tell us, that were our ſelves at the like diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage with our Profeſſion, we might be as ready to plead for a Toleration as others: For, we find Chriſt and his Apoſtles, when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veened before Magiſtrates, never made uſe of that defence, That a Toleration in Religion (be what it will) was due from the Civil Magiſtrate, but pleaded ſtill the truth of their Doctrine: And though <hi>Paul</hi> was frequently under perſecution; yet we find him againſt Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.11, with 12. Nor was <hi>Elijah</hi> the leſſe zealous againſt falſe Prophets, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.40. that there was a <hi>Jezebel</hi> ready to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute himſelf, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.2. And though we be encompaſſed with infirmities; yet, in ſo far as we have obtained mercy, we are ready to ſay (as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Act.</hi> 25.11.) That if we followed any errour, we refuſe not to be reſtrained in it, and ſhould count our ſelves moſt unhappy if we were inſtrumental to propagate any errour, and ſet our ſelves to overturn a bleſſed work of Reformation in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
            <p>Having thus briefly pointed at the ſinfulneſſe of this courſe, We do in the fear of the Lord warn all theſe (eſpecially within our charge) who have an hand in this matter, to conſider from whence they have fallen and to repent; and do exhort them in the bowels of Chriſt, that they do examine impartially what their deſigns are, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they have engaged in this courſe, ſo deſtructive to their Mother-Church, and the Truths of Chriſt eſtabliſhed in her; and that they forbear to proſecute the pulling down of an hedge, to let in Popery and Atheiſm, leſt a Serpent bite them. We are not ignorant
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99133:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>how pleaſing licentious liberty is to the fleſh; yet their conſciences will eaſily tell them, that it was none of <hi>Adam's</hi> happineſſe to have more room out of <hi>Paradiſe</hi> than within it, And that it is no mercy for men to have liberty to do every one what is right in his own eves, which hath been the plague and ſad poſture of the Church of God in her declining times. We do likewiſe exhort all the Lord's people within our bounds, as to mourn before the Lord in behalf of thoſe who have declined, and that ſuch abominations ſhould find any to owne them among us; So alſo rightly to improve ſuch humbling diſpenſations; That they ſtudy ſobriety of mind, the want whereof hath miſcarried ſo many; That they receive the love of the Truth, for the neglect whereof, God is provoked to ſend ſtrong deluſions; That they converſe more in the ſtudy of their own ſinfulneſſe, and the ſufficiency of Chriſt, which being ſtill ſavoury, will keep them from gadding after novelties in Religion; That they improve Ordinances as becometh, leſt reſted-in formality draw on contempt of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; That they would unite among themſelves in matters of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour differences, that ſo they may joyntly lay forth themſelves, in their ſtations, for obſtructing the progreſſe of this deluge, which is ready to ſwallow up all Religion; And that they imploy Chriſt much, who is the King and Head of his own Church, that by His own Spirit he would interpoſe to ſtop the current of theſe Deluſions and Defections, that Truth, and Peace, and Holineſſe may yet flouriſh in the midſt of us. <hi>Even ſo, Come, Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
